<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of enthusiasm exorcised in a sermon preached before the University of Oxford, on Act-Sunday, July 11, 1680 / by George Hickes.</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11821422</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11821422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 496:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of enthusiasm exorcised in a sermon preached before the University of Oxford, on Act-Sunday, July 11, 1680 / by George Hickes.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, XII, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Enthusiasm --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49584:1"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is newly publiſhed a Volume of <hi>LXI. Sermons,</hi> Preached by the ſame Author. Printed for <hi>Rich. Marriott;</hi> and Sold by moſt Book-Sellers in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49584:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Spirit of Enthuſiaſm</hi> EXORCISED. IN A SERMON PREACHED Before the UNIVERSITY OF OXFORD, on ACT-SUNDAY, <hi>July</hi> 11. 1680.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Hickes</hi> D. D. Prebendary of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at the requeſt of Mr. <hi>Vice-Chancellor,</hi> and many others, who heard it Preached.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Diſerti ſunt multi inter illos, magnae linguae, flumina linguarum, nunquid Angelicè loquuntur? — omnia illa nihil iis proſunt, quia conſcindunt unitatem— <hi>Paulus</hi> loquitur, <hi>ſi ſciam omnia ſacramenta,</hi> &amp;c. Nemo ergo vobis fabulas vendat, &amp; Pontius fecit miraculum, &amp; <hi>Donatus oravit,</hi> &amp; Deus ei reſpondit de Coelo.— Crederem ſi non <hi>diviſiſſet unitatem,</hi> nam &amp; contra iſtos (ut ſic loquar) mirabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarios cautum me fecit Deus meus dicens, <hi>in noviſſimis temporibus.</hi>—teneamus ergo unitatem fratres mei, prater unitatem, &amp; qui facit miracula nihil eſt.— Proinde fratres mei nemo vos fallat. nemo vos ſeducat, amate pacem Chriſti, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. exp. in Evang. Johan. tract. 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s-<hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49584:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Doctor TIMOTHY HALTON Provoſt of <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS-COLLEDGE,</hi> and VICE-CHANCELLOR Of the UNIVERSITY of OXFORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe, which was ſo acceptable to You from the Pulpit, comes now in all Humility from the Preſs to offer it ſelf to your further Acceptance, and Protection, and to the Peruſal of all thoſe Learned, and Orthodox men, who deſired me to Publiſh it, as containing ſome Sober, and wholſom doctrines, which they judged ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the age. I had a mind to ſatisfie my ſelf in this Subject, and having by Gods bleſſing upon my enquiries attained to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in them, I framed my Obſervations on purpoſe into a Sermon, to ſee if happily I could ſatisfie other mens reaſons, by the ſame Arguments, by which I had convinced my own. And becauſe <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets,</hi> I choſe to Preach it in that Audience, where are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo many Competent and able Judges of Truth and Error, and what I ſaid on that obſcure Subject (as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calls it) having been approved therein, I am encouraged to hope, that it will find the like Entertainment in other places, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally among all ingenuous ſpirits, who are wont to read with unprejudiced minds. But leſt any ſhould think, that the Scheme, by which I go in this Diſcourſe, were an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of my own inventing, I have confirmed the paſſages in it,
<pb facs="tcp:49584:3"/> which I thought would be moſt ſurprizing, with good Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities: becauſe how plauſible ſoever any Notions in Divinity may be, yet they may reaſonably paſs for ſuſpected, unleſs they appear to be agreeable to the Sentiments of the Writers of the <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Church. To write all things conſonantly to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Antiquity is a ſafe and excellent rule, and it is for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to it in her Doctrine and Diſcipline, that the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and Her Clergy have been always perſecuted by the Papiſts, thoſe <hi>Pſeudo-Catholicks</hi> on one hand, and their Inſtruments, the <hi>Anti-Prelatical</hi> Sects on the other; and becauſe under God the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities are the ſupport of the Church, therefore have they been decryed for want of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>thoſe,</hi> and want of Virtue and Religion by <hi>theſe,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have been, and are as fruitful Seminaries of both, as any <hi>Schools,</hi> or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities that are, or ever were in the world. And now having occaſion to ſpeak of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, it would be real injuſtice to your Merits, not to let the world know, how happy ours is in Your Government. I might juſtly ſpeak great things of Your Severity in puniſhing of Vice, of the great encouragement you give to Virtue, and Learning, and of your Care and Vigilance both over your own Colledge, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, particularly in giving life to the Publick Exerciſes in the Schools, of which you are in all Arts and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties ſo great a Judge. It is under ſuch Governours as You, that the Muſes will flouriſh in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that true Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Sound Religion will always be taught therein. And therefore that there may never want a Succeſſion of ſuch <hi>Vice-Chancellours</hi> as You to Govern that Famous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, nor of ſuch Learned Maſters, and Scholars, as now adorn it, is the hearty prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged and Humble Servant, <hi>GEORGE HICKES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49584:3"/>
            <head>THE SPIRIT OF Enthuſiaſm EXORCISED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. xii. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now there are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame Spirit.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Diſcourſe, which I intend to make upon this Verſe, will oblige me to explain the moſt obſcure, and difficult paſſages of this Chapter; from the miſunderſtanding of which, and moſt other places of the Goſpel, which ſpeak of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> gifts, Impoſtors on one hand, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſts on the other have raiſed ſuch abſurd and exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant doctrines, as are utterly inconſiſtent, not only with the uſe and Authority of the Scriptures, but the Tradition of the Univerſal Church, the Orders of the Miniſtery, and the Study of Divinity, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence render the Chriſtian Religion, which conſiſts of ſuch Sober and Rational Doctrines, the moſt wild, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49584:4"/> and unintelligible inſtitution that ever was in the world. But how groundleſs and unwarrantable the Enthuſiaſtical Interpretations of this, and other like places of Scripture are, will appear from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this Diſcourſe, in which I intend to treat ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of the Gifts of the Spirit, as to leave out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which may be ſaid in ſuch a ſhort Diſcourſe, to illuſtrate ſuch an excellent Subject, the knowledge of which is a moſt Soveraign Antidote againſt the poiſon of Enthuſiaſm, which is the Spiritual drunkenneſs, or Lunacy of this Schiſmatical age, and ſo diſtempers the minds of men of the other Communions with extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant phancies, as to make them more or leſs affect the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit, and then conceit, like Poets in Religion, that they have them, and are inſpired.</p>
            <p>Thus much I thought convenient to premiſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter and deſign of this Diſcourſe, in which I ſhall proceed according to this familiar method. Firſt, I intend to ſpeak of the ſeveral kinds of Spiritual gifts, and ſhew which ſort is mentioned in my Text. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhall treat of the number and variety of them, and explain the nature of each particular gift. Thirdly, I ſhall diſcourſe of the true uſe of them, and ſhew the reaſons, why they were given by God to the Primitive Church, and not to the Churches of latter times. And Laſtly, I ſhall make ſome Practical improvement of the whole diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt then as to the kinds of theſe Spiritual gifts, I know my Text is often miſapplyed by way of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation to ſignifie the natural, or acquired gifts of mans mind, which in a Phyſical ſenſe indeed may be called Spiritual, becauſe they tranſcend the Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal powers of matter, and proceed more or leſs from the rational ſoul, which is a Spiritual ſubſtance, and as near a-kin in nature to the Father of Spirits as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49584:4"/> his eldeſt Sons can be. Such gifts and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as theſe are <hi>Memory, Fancy, Wit, Eloquence,</hi> and all Organical powers, which are commonly known by the name of <hi>Natural parts,</hi> but more eſpecially the pure intellectual powers of <hi>Apprehending</hi> and <hi>Judging, Comparing, Ordering</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſing,</hi> many, or all of both which kinds ſome happy Souls poſſeſs in ſuch abundance, and perfection, as gives them, according to <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> obſervation, a natural kind of Superiority over their companions, and fits them to govern, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the world.</p>
            <p>But then how much ſoever ſome men may tranſcend others in their intellectual capacities, and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we muſt not like the Poets, aſcribe their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts to an higher principle, than the nature of man. For the talleſt Trees are natural, as well as the loweſt ſhrubs; and Gigantick Souls, as well as bodies, how prodigious ſoever their ſtature may be, yet, like <hi>Saul</hi> among his brethren, they are but men, though worthy to be Princes, and differ as much from perſons gifted by inſpiration, as <hi>Goliah</hi> from <hi>Samſon, Praxiteles</hi> and <hi>Phidias</hi> from <hi>Bezaliel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> or <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died Linguiſts</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were inſpired with the gift of tongues.</p>
            <p>Indeed all our parts and abilities are the gifts of God, who is the original Author of our nature, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of all that belongs thereunto; but the Gifts of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks in this Chapter, are wholly Supernatural, and immediately proceed from the Spirit of God. Gifts that were given to advance humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above it ſelf, to raiſe all its Springs above their Fountain, and enable the bleſſed perſons affected with them to ſpeak, and write, and act ſuch things, and in ſuch a peculiar manner, as was impoſſible for men not inſpired to do.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Gifts, or Graces, which the Apoſtle
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49584:5"/> treats of in this Chapter, as may be proved from the firſt verſe, which is an Introduction to his whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Now Brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Spiritual gifts I would not have you ignorant. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual gifts,</hi> not ſo called from the ſoul, or ſpirit of man, wherein they were as in their ſubject (for if this had been his meaning, he muſt not have ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but the author from whom they came <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> whom our Saviour promiſed to ſend to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after he aſcended into Heaven; which he firſt of all did on the day of Pentecoſt, when the Holy Ghoſt came down upon them in a mighty ruſhing wind to ſignifie the plentiful Inſpiration of the Spirit, and ſat upon them all in the ſhape of fiery cloven tongues, as ſo many viſible Symbols of the moſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. Hom. <hi>29.</hi> in <hi>1</hi> ep. ad Cor. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> wonderful act of Inſpiration, which was the gift of tongues.</p>
            <p>But then there being Two ſorts of Spiritual gifts <hi>common,</hi> and <hi>ſpecial,</hi> we muſt further proceed to enquire which kind of the Two is meant here.</p>
            <p>By the common gifts of the Spirit, I mean all thoſe, that all Chriſtians are bound to pray for, and expect, and that are given by God in common to all thoſe who ſincerely deſire them, and labour after them, and that are neceſſary for the Salvation of the Soul.</p>
            <p>By Special gifs I underſtand thoſe, which men are not ordinarily bound to expect, and which, unleſs it be in ſome few circumſtances, that ſeldom happen, would be vanity and preſumption to beg of God, and which by conſequence are not neceſſary for the Salvation of the Soul.</p>
            <p>Of the former ſort are all the ſaving Gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit called in the Schools, <hi>gratiae gratum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes,</hi> which the Spirit helps to work in mens hearts, as <hi>Faith, Hope, Charity, Purity, Humility,</hi> and all other gracious habits of mind, which the Apoſtle calls the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49584:5"/> fruit of the Spirit, and wherein the image of God, the Power of Godlineſs, and the Spirit of Chriſtianity truly do conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Of the latter ſort are all the Miraculous Unctions of the Holy Ghoſt, called by the Schoolmen, <hi>gratiae gratis datae,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>gift of tongues, power of working mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſigns and wonders, the ſpirit of Prophecy,</hi> and the like, which are not neceſſary for the Church, but in certain caſes of ſpecial exigence, and which, when they are neceſſary, are not given, like the other, joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all, but ſeverally to ſome. Such wonderful gifts and graces were thoſe, which <hi>Elias</hi> ſent down with his Mantle upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> when he aſcended into Heaven, thereby prefiguring the liberal effuſion of the Spirit from Chriſt upon his Diſciples after his Aſcenſion; for as the Apoſtle writes in the 4th Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians, When he aſcended up on high, and led Captivity</hi> (that is, Satan, Sin, and death) <hi>captive, he gave in like manner gifts unto men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe ſorts of gifts agree in this, that they are Supernatural, and freely given by God to men, and therefore both of them are called <hi>gratiae</hi> in the vulgar Latin, and <hi>Graces</hi> in all the modern tongues, though for diſtinction ſake the former are commonly called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the latter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by Divines. But though both proceed from the ſame Spirit, and ſpring from the ſame Fountain of <hi>Grace,</hi> yet, as I have already hinted, they differ in their <hi>nature, extent,</hi> and <hi>uſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt in their Nature: for the former are nothing, but moral vertues inſenſibly wrought in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, we our ſelves co-operating therewith. And their proper effect is to ſanctifie our nature, and make us like, and acceptable unto God. But the latter are not of a moral nature, nor capable of moral conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as being either pure intellectual habits, as the gift of Tongues, diſcerning of Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49584:6"/> virtues, and powers, as the power of Curing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which the affected perſon contributed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing himſelf, and by which though he were made a more eminent man, or Miniſter, yet was he not made a <note n="*" place="margin">Non omnes Chriſtiani boni daemones ejici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, omnium ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men nomina ſcripta ſunt in Coelo. <hi>Auguſt. in Pſ. 130.</hi>
               </note> better Chriſtian than he was before. Therefore they did not ſanctifie the nature of the perſon, on whom they were beſtow'd, nor render him in the leaſt more acceptable unto God, though they were (ſome of them more eſpecially) often given to ſanctified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſo might declare, but not make a man good. I ſay they were often, but not always given to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons: for at <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theophyl. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>12.1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chryſoſt. in Epiſt. ad Rom. cap. <hi>8.</hi> Hom. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> firſt the Holy Ghoſt fell upon all that were Baptized, and Confirmed; the Spirit of Prophecy was given to <hi>Balaam;</hi> the Power of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Signs and Wonders, and of caſting out Devils was given to <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <bibl>Hieronym. in cap. 7. Matth.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Multi mihi dicent,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Judas,</hi> as well as the reſt of the Apoſtles; and therefore ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.23. to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Many will ſay unto me in that day</hi> (that is, the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <note n="c" place="margin">Si ſciam <hi>(inquit)</hi> omnia Sacramenta— charitatem autem non habeam, nihil ſum. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ergo vobis fabulas vendai: &amp; Pontius fecit miraculum &amp; Donatus oravit, &amp; reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Deus ei de Coelo—contra iſtos, ut ſic lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quar, mirabiliarios cautum me fecit Deus meus dicens, In noviſſimis temporibus, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Aug. tract. 13. in Evang. Johan. Cyprian de unit. Eccleſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lord! Lord! have we not propheſied in thy name, and in thy name have done many wonderful works? and then will I profeſs unto you, I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi> From which place it is evident, that Miraculous gifts are ſo far from transforming the ſinful nature of man, that if they do not find us, they cannot make us good, nor, like a ſingle act of Faith and Repentance, give us a Title to the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49584:6"/>
            <p>Then as for their extent, the latter are not uſeful for all Churches, nor for the ſame Church in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and ſtates; and in the Churches where they were uſeful, they were, as it appears from Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtory, commonly given to the Miniſters more than the people, to children not at all, and ſeldomer to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men than to men. But the Saving graces of the Spirit are equally uſeful for the Church in all conditions and ſtates, and are given as much to the people as to their Miniſters, and to women and children, as much as to men, and they are never taken from thoſe, to whom they are once given unleſs they neglect, or abuſe them, and grieve the good Spirit from whom they come.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As for their uſe, the Saving gifts are given to men for their own, but the Miraculous gifts for the good of the Church. By Thoſe we vanquiſh the Devil, and deſtroy his kingdom of ſin within us; by Theſe the Apoſtles deſtroyed his kingdom of darkneſs in the Idolatrous world: By Thoſe we Glorifie God within the Pale of the Church; by Theſe we publiſh his Almighty Power and Glory to thoſe without. Laſtly, Thoſe make us precious in the eyes of God, Theſe make us glorious in the eyes of men. Whereupon Gifted perſons, as it appears from the 4th <hi>ch.</hi> of this Epiſt. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. were often tempted by popular applauſe to pride themſelves in their gifts. For this reaſon it was, as the Apoſtle ſuggeſts in the 11th <hi>ver.</hi> that God divided theſe Gifts to ſeveral men in ſeveral meaſures and proportions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he knew their capacities would bear. For ſuch is the infirmity of humane nature, that the beſt of Gifted men were apt to <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>29.</hi> in <hi>1</hi> Ep. ad Cor. c. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> glorifie themſelves in their Gifts, and deſpiſe the Un-gifted Miniſters of the Church. For which reaſon there was <hi>given a</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Ne extollere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tanquam j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>venis, colaphizabatur tanquam puer—ſi ergo Apoſtolus potuit extolli magnitudine revelationum, niſi acciperet Angelum Satanae, qui ſe colathizaret— vidit Dominus quod tentaret cos ſuperbias ex potentis miraculorum. <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal. 130.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>thorn in the fleſh</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49584:7"/> to this bleſſed Apoſtle himſelf, <hi>and the meſſenger of Satan to buffet him, leſt he ſhould be exalted above meaſure through the abundance of revelations, which he received.</hi> And therefore knowing, that theſe miraculous graces were valuable no further, than as they were ſerviceable to the Church, he reproved the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in the laſt verſe of this, and the beginning of the next Chapter for their immoderate ambitious deſiring of them, exhorting them rather to covet, and pray earneſtly for the ſaving graces of the Spirit, as the more deſirable gifts.</p>
            <p>From which compariſon, and likewiſe from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral diſtributions of theſe gifts, of which he treats in this Chapter, it is moſt certain, that he underſtood by them not the ſaving univerſal, but the ſpecial miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. For as he ſpeaks in the 8th and 9th verſes, to one was given one Gift, to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther another, to a third a third; to every man ſeverally to one greater to another leſs, according as God in his wiſdom ſaw fit. Which cannot be truly ſaid of the Saving Graces of the Spirit, becauſe God muſt beſtow them joyntly, or not at all. God cannot give Humility to one, Purity, or Chaſtneſs to another, and Charity alone to a third, becauſe there is ſuch an inſeparable union and alliance among the Graces of the Spirit (as Philoſophers have obſerved of Moral vertues) that where one is really, there all the reſt muſt be. Which, as I conceive, is the reaſon why the Writers of the New Teſtament expreſs the whole body of Practical Divinity ſometimes by Faith, ſometimes by Hope, ſometimes by Repentance, and ſometimes by Love, becauſe the combination of theſe Saving Graces is ſuch, that the mentioning of one implies all the reſt.</p>
            <p>But if this be not ſufficient to prove, eſpecially againſt Enthuſiaſts, that by Spiritual gifts in this place the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſort of them is to be underſtood, it will unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably appear from conſidering the number and variety
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49584:7"/> of them, of which I propoſed to ſpeak in the ſecond place. <hi>For there are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great diverſity indeed, for the Apoſtle here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents us with a liſt of Nine ſorts. <hi>The Word of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; the Word of Knowledge; Faith; Gifts of Healing; Working of Miracles; Prophecy; diſcerning of Spirits; diverſe kinds of Tongues; and the interpretation of thoſe Tongues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, The Word of Wiſdom, or the Revelation of the Goſpel, which is called the Wiſdom of God in Chriſt. For as the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> called the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſecret and excellent things by the name of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy: So the <hi>Jews</hi> called it by the name of <hi>Choch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah,</hi> or Wiſdom, which ſo often occurs in <hi>Solomons</hi> works. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Helleniſtical ſtyle, which conſiſted in writing of Hebraiſms, or Syriaciſms, in <hi>Greek,</hi> Emphatically calls the knowledge of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem ſapientiae vocat non eloquentiam ſed veram doctrinam, cujus ipſe etiam divinus Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus gratiam acceperat, &amp; divus <hi>Johan.</hi> Evangeliſta, &amp; divus <hi>Petrus</hi> Apoſtolorum ſummus. Neque enim potuiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt homines piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores, &amp; manu ſibi victum parantes, &amp; lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum planè ignari conciones habere, &amp; ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, &amp; quae dicebant, &amp; ſcriptis mandabant virtute maximâ implere, niſi à divino Spiritu veram ſapientiam accepiſſent. <hi>Theodoret.</hi> in <hi>2 ep.</hi> ad <hi>Corinth. cap. 12.</hi>
               </note> Evangelical do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and myſteries by the name of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and diſtinguiſheth it from the Wiſdom, <hi>i. e.</hi> from the Philoſophy of the world, in the 2d ch. of this Epiſt. 6, and 7. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Howbeit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we ſpeak wiſdom, yet not the wiſdom of this world, but the wiſdom of God in a myſtery, even the hidden wiſdom, the revelation of which, God ordained before the world was unto our,</hi> that is, unto the glory of us the Apoſtles, who were the firſt diſcoverers thereof. To them it was that the Spirit gave the Firſt Underſtanding and diſcovery of the Myſteries of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt; in whom, as our Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49584:8"/> of Wiſdom and Knowledge were hid. In him they were hidden, and wrapt up, before they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded by the Apoſtles, to whom in the 14, 15, and 16. Chapters of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel our Saviour promiſed his Spirit to comfort and aſſiſt them in his abſence, to teach them all the things that belonged to the Goſpel, to lead them into all truth, to bring to their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, whatſoever he had formerly taught them, and bear witneſs to the Truth of their Doctrine by his works. Therefore the firſt, and moſt principal gift of the Spirit was this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Revelation of the Goſpel, or the diſcovery of all thoſe excellent truths, the knowledge and belief whereof is Eſſential on our parts to the New and better Covenant, which God hath made betwixt himſelf and man. This Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral knowledge of the <hi>whole</hi> Counſel of God in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the world through Chriſt, was firſt given to the Apoſtles by the Inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, and Preached by them to the whole world. Given I ſay, to the Apoſtles, for as we read of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>diverſities of gifts</hi> in my Text: So in the next <hi>verſe</hi> to it, we read of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>differences of Adminiſtrations,</hi> that is, of Miniſteries, or Miniſters, to whom theſe Gifts belonged. And therefore as the Apoſtle hath put the <hi>word of Wiſdom</hi> firſt in the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of gifts: So in the Liſt of Miniſters, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to it in the 28th <hi>verſe,</hi> he hath put the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> firſt.</p>
            <p>From whence I paſs to the word of Knowledge, by which with Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> and <hi>Menochius,</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Prophecy properly ſo called, or the revealed knowledge of ſecret, remote, and future things. Of ſecret things, as of the mind, or will of God, or the thoughts of men; of remote things, as of what was done in other places; or of future things, as of what would be done in times to come. According to this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49584:8"/> Interpretation you will find, that <hi>Prophets,</hi> which holds the Second place in the Liſt of Miniſters, exactly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the <hi>word of Knowledge</hi> in the Catalogue of Gifts. <hi>In the Church</hi> (ſaith he) God hath ſet Firſt Apoſtles, Secondarily Prophets. The Spirit of Prophecy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called had ceaſed a long time in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church before the coming of Chriſt; but in the <hi>laſt days,</hi> that is, in the concluſion of the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Chriſtian Church, God poured it out upon all fleſh, and their young men ſaw Viſions, and their old men dreamed Dreams, according to the prediction of <hi>Joel</hi> in the 2d chap. which St. <hi>Peter</hi> on the day of Pentecoſt, when the Spirit deſcended with all his Gifts, declared was fulfilled to the <hi>Jews.</hi> By this renewed Spirit of Prophecy it was, that the <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 13 2.</note> Prophets in the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> had it revealed to them by the Holy Ghoſt, that <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould be ſeparated for the work, unto which he had called them; that St. <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 5.3.</note> knew, that <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> lyed to the Holy Ghoſt; that <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 11.28.21.10.</note> 
               <hi>Agabus</hi> foretold the Farmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the days of <hi>Claudius Caeſar,</hi> and the impriſonment of St. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Ananias</hi> knew of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and that <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 27.23, 24.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion before the Shipwrack that not a man in the ſhip ſhould be loſt. Laſtly, that St. <hi>John</hi> wrote the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the ancient Prophetick ſtyle, and that many others, of whom we read in <note n="‖" place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>37</hi>
               </note> Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, foretold many ſtrange events.</p>
            <p>From whence I proceed to the Third Gift, which is called <hi>Faith,</hi> by which you are not to underſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <note n="*" place="margin">Hom. <hi>29.</hi> in Ep. ad Cor. cap. <hi>12.</hi> Theophyl &amp; Oecum. &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. in id. cap.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> calls juſtifying, or ſaving Faith, (for that was a common gift to which all Chriſtians had an equal title and claim) but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the faith of Miracles Emphatically ſo called, becauſe it was a certain ſupernatural confidence, and aſſurance wrought by the Spirit in the Soul of a man, by which he was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49584:9"/> ſure he could do ſuch or ſuch Miracles, before he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to do them. By this ſupernatural confidence, and impulſe it was, that men knew, as by a ſign, when they could work wonders, and when not, and the greateſt Operator, whether Prophet, or Apoſtle durſt never undertake to do a Miracle, but when he was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the Spirit he could do it. And indeed it was requiſite for God by ſome ſecret preceeding impreſſion to let the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Teachers of the Goſpel know, when he would aſſiſt them, leſt they ſhould attempt to do Miracles when they could not, and ſo diſcredit their own Doctrine, and Authority, and diſhonour the name of God. Of this ſort of Enthuſiaſtical confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with which the Spirit filled the minds of men, is that place to be underſtood in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>As alſo that in</hi> Matth. <hi>17.20.</hi> Luke <hi>17.5, 6.</hi> vid. Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>29.</hi> in <hi>1</hi> cp. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. cap. <hi>12.</hi> —<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Theodor. in locum. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</note> 21. <hi>ch.</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. where our Saviour told his Diſciples, <hi>That if they had faith, and doubted not, they ſhould not only do what he had done to the fig-tree, but if they ſhould ſay to that mountain</hi> (upon which they ſtood) <hi>Be thou removed, and caſt into the ſea, it ſhould be done.</hi> And therefore this ſort of Faith is here put before the Gift of healing, and working of Miracles, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in an antecedent impulſe to do both.</p>
            <p>Or elſe by Faith is here to be underſtood <hi>ſupernatural courage, and confidence,</hi> with which God was wont to endow the minds of all thoſe, whom he ſet upon any deſign, that would find oppoſitions from Devils or men. This <hi>fiducia,</hi> or undanted courage is called in the New Teſtament <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we render boldneſs, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.13, 29, 31. But by the ingenious Tranſlator of the <hi>Mons-teſtament</hi> it is rendered <hi>Conſtance, fermeté, Liberté, Hardieſſe,</hi> and it was an effect of that which the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> writers call the <hi>Spirit of might,</hi> and as <note n="‖" place="margin">More Nevoch. p. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maimonides</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49584:9"/> it was always conferr'd upon the perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by God after the promiſe of <hi>ittecha Ani,</hi> or <hi>Ehieh Immach, Go, and I will be with thee.</hi> Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe as it was ſolemnly made by God to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 1 8.</note> 
               <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.6, 8. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.5.</note> others in the Old Teſtament: So was it as ſolemnly made to the Apoſtles by Chriſt in the New. For after his Reſurrection, when he gave them Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Authority to Teach, and Baptize all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, He ſaid, <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>All power is given unto me both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and lo! I am with you to the end of the world.</hi> Accordingly we read in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, with what invincible reſolution and courage thoſe poor men appeared before the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and Heathen Tribunals, and with what aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing preſence both of body and mind, they, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 72.</note> other Teachers of the Goſpel, bore the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> before the Kings, and Princes, and people of the earth.</p>
            <p>Under the Fourth miraculous Gift, which is the gift of Healing is comprehended the power of Curing all diſeaſes both of body, and <note n="*" place="margin">Inde jam facultas datur poſſe venenorum virus extinguere, animorum deſipientium la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes redditâ ſanitate purgare, infeſtis jubere pacem, violentis quictem, ferocientibus leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,— <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt. ad Donat.</hi>
               </note> mind without the help of Phyſick through the alone name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, as alſo the more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful power of raiſing the dead. For as inflicting of death is uſually joyned by the Ancients with the power of inflicting diſeaſes: So the power of Curing diſeaſes, and raiſing the dead are uſually joyned together in their <note n="‖" place="margin">Alii laborantes aliquâ infirmitate per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nûs impoſitionem curant &amp; ſanos reſtituunt, etiam &amp; quemaedmodum diximus mortui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrexerunt; &amp; perſeverârant nobiſcum annis multis. Irenaeus, <hi>lib. 2. c. 57. vid. Euſeb. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hiſt. c. 7.</hi>
               </note> writings as effects of the ſame miraculous gift. Although the latter alſo is often reduced under the Fifth miraculous gift, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we tranſlate work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miracles: under which is comprehended the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49584:10"/> power of working ſigns and wonders in the Heavens, of ſilencing, and caſting Devils both out of Men, and Oracles, of inflicting death, as the Prophet did on the Captains of Fifties, and their Companies, and St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and his wife. Laſtly, the power of inflicting Diſeaſes on the bodies of incorrigible ſinners, as <hi>Paul</hi> did upon <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer, which in this, and the firſt of his Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> is called the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering up to Satan by Excommunication, and perhaps alſo the power of filling the Souls of contumacious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with ſupernatural horrour, and agonies, which when they are but natural are worſe to be endured, than the moſt intolerable bodily pains.</p>
            <p>By Prophecy is not underſtood the gift of Prediction, or knowing remote, and future events. But firſt, the gift of Preaching or expounding the Scriptures by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, in which ſenſe it is ſaid in the 4th <hi>verſe</hi> of the 11th <hi>chap.</hi> every man Praying or Propheſying, that is, Praying and Preaching with his head covered diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth his head. In this ſence Inſpired Preachers are called Prophets in the 14th <hi>chap.</hi> of this Epiſt. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>Let the Prophets</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſpeak two, or three at a time, and let the reſt hear, and judg.</hi> Accordingly <hi>Nebia</hi> the Hebrew word for a Prophet is often rendred in the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Tranſlation by <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Targ. Jon.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Siphra,</hi> and <note n="‖" place="margin">Targ. Onk. Exod. <hi>7.1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Meturgeman</hi> which ſignifies Teacher, and Interpreter, in which ſence the Preachers in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were very properly called Prophets, who Preached, and expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Holy Scriptures by Inſpiration from the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Or elſe Prophecy may be taken, as it often is in the Old, and New Teſtament, for <hi>Praiſing of God by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Hymns and Pſalms.</hi> For inſpired perſons did uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſpend their Enthuſiaſm in compoſing of Hymns, and Spiritual ſongs: which is the reaſon we read of ſuch a great number of Divine Poets, or Pſalmiſts among
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49584:10"/> the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> as <hi>Moſes, David, Aſaph, Heman, Jedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thun,</hi> and the reſt. Hence it is that we read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. of a company of Prophets, who came down from an high place Propheſying, Singing (ſaith the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt) with Pſalteries, Tabrets, Pipes and Harps. And both in that, and the 19th <hi>chap.</hi> where <hi>Saul</hi> is ſaid to have Propheſied among the Prophets; the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt</hi> plainly ſaith he Sang, or Praiſed God. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to both theſe ſenſes of the word <hi>Prophecy</hi> you find Pſalms, and Doctrines among the gifts of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the 24th <hi>chap.</hi> of this Epiſt. and the 26 <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thirdly, Prophecy is put here not only for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Praiſing God by Inſpiration, but alſo for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him <hi>in publick Aſſemblies</hi> by <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro unà cum his omnibus donis erat &amp; precum donum, <hi>quod &amp; ipſum ſpiritus dicebatur,</hi> quo qui praeditus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat <hi>pro plebe universâ preces ſundebat.</hi> Quandoquidem enim multa eorum, quae nobis conducunt, ignorcmus, &amp; quae minime conducunt poſtulemus, acceſſit donum precum ad unum aliquem corum, qui quod com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitèr univerſae Eccleſiae conducebat, id ipſe <hi>pro omnibus ſtans poſtularet,</hi> tum alios edoceret. <hi>Spiritum igitur hic vocat tum donum tale, tum animam eam, quae donum id ſuſciperet,</hi> quaeque apud Deum intercederet, ac gemeret. Qui enim hujuſmodi gratiá dignatus eſt, is magnâ cum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi compunctione ſtins, multiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cum gemitibus mente autem coram Deo proſtratus quae omnibus conducunt petit, <hi>cujus &amp; nunc Symbolum eſt Miniſter pro populo preces Deo offerens.</hi> Hoc igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Paulus ſentiens dixit, <hi>ipſe ſpiritus intercedit pro nobis gemitibus menarrabilibus.</hi> Chryſ. in ep. ad Rom. c <hi>8.</hi> Hom. <hi>14. To the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks</hi> Theoph. <hi>and</hi> Occumen. <hi>upon the place.</hi>
               </note> Inſpired Prayers. For in the Apoſtles time there was a Miraculous gift of Praying as well as Preaching, when the Spirit uſed to ſeize upon the Souls of men in publick, and affect them in ſuch an extraordinary way as to make them pray for ſuch things, and in ſuch a due manner, as in thoſe times, when as yet the Church had compoſed no Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, perſons not Inſpired could not do.</p>
            <p>In this ſenſe it was, that the Apoſtle ſaith that the Spirit (or gift of the Spirit) helpeth our infirmities. And that the Spirit, or <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— nam magnâ cum compunctione ſtabat ſpiritualis ille homo, &amp; multis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gemitibus, cujus hodiè fignum eſt <hi>Diaconus ſtans</hi> intentas ſupplicationes pro populo effund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Theoph. in locum.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </note> Inſpired perſon, maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with <hi>unutterable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49584:11"/> ſighs and groans.</hi> Likewiſe (ſaith he) the Spirit help-our infirmities, <hi>for</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Etiam ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum immiſcuit nè ſermo odio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus videatur. <hi>Oecumen. in locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we know not what we ſhould pray for,</hi> [or in what manner] <hi>as we ought,</hi> but the inſpired man maketh interceſſion for us with groanings which cannot be expreſſed. Which groanings were the effect of thoſe ſupernatural raptures, and Enthuſiaſms, with which the Spirit filled the Souls of theſe Inſpired Orators, often moving them withal to Pray in unknown tongues. Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> Emphatically calls <hi>praying by the ſpirit,</hi> in oppoſition to praying intelligibly, or with the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as you may ſee in the <note n="‖" place="margin">Chryſoſt. &amp; Theoph. in loc.</note> 14th <hi>chap.</hi> of this Epiſt. the 14 and 15 <hi>verſes,</hi> which the Enthuſiaſts of this age have ſo perverted, and abuſed. This Gift above all others was looked upon as a ſingular pledge of Gods favour, and as a Seal by which he own'd the Chriſtians to be his <hi>adopted Sons.</hi> And therefore in the 8th <hi>chap.</hi> of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> the Apoſtle calls it the <hi>Spirit of Adoption,</hi> whereby they were moved to cry <hi>Abba Father.</hi> A name as St. <note n="*" place="margin">In locum.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> and <hi>Theophyl.</hi> obſerve, by which the <hi>Jews</hi> were no where found to call upon God in Prayer, although they called God <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.18. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Chron</hi> 29.10. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 63.16.64.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.41. So Joma <hi>c.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>dixit R. Akiba beati vos O Iſrael coram quo purificamini; &amp; quis purificat vos?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ater veſler qui eſt in Coelis, <hi>juxta dictum illud &amp; ſpargam, &amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 36.25. Sotta cap. 9. 15. <hi>Poſtquam praedixit futuras ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitatos tempore viſitationis templi ſic erum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit: Cui ergo nitemur</hi> niſi Patri noſtio, qui eſt in Coelis? quae verba bis ibi repetun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> Father, by way of acknowledgment and confeſſion, and therefore the Spirit moving the Chriſtians to invoke God by the name of Father, as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had directed his Diſciples to addreſs themſelves unto him before, did thereby bear witneſs with their Spirits, that they were <hi>the Sons of God.</hi> I pray mark what I ſay upon the Authority of St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> who aſſerts that the <hi>Jews</hi> were <hi>no where</hi> found to invoke God by the name of Father, which muſt be <note n="*" place="margin">For in their Offices which are very anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, we find God invoked by the name of <hi>Father,</hi> particularly in that ſolemn Prayer, which is ſtiled (becauſe it contains Eighteen ſmall prayers) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and mention whereof is made in the <hi>Miſhna [tractat. de Benedictionibus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> cap.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>Ramban Gamaliel dicit quâlibet die orare debet quiſquam octodecem preces]</hi> one of thoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers beginneth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>fac nos revertere Pater noſter ad legem tuam.</hi> Turn us our Father unto thy Law. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prayer for the bleſſing of the ſeaſon of the year, which particularly is cited in the <hi>Miſna</hi> in the ſame tract. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. 2. beginneth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bleſs us,</hi> our Father, <hi>in all the works of our hands.</hi> In the days appointed for penitence which are 10 days, and to ſome 40 before the day of atonement, there are many prayers, which begin <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>our Father, our King.</hi> But though this title of <hi>Father</hi> be now found in the Prayers of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> yet it is very probable that they being under a ſervile diſpenſation very rarely preſumed to addreſs themſelves unto God by that familiar appellation, till they ſaw that the Chriſtians, who reproached them as <hi>bondmen to the law,</hi> came with ſuch freedom to the throne of Grace.</note> reſtrained to the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> and the <hi>Apocrypha;</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49584:11"/> where from <hi>Abraham</hi> to the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abeans</hi> we find none that calls upon him in Prayer by the name of <hi>Father,</hi> which makes this Great mans notion very probable, that the Chriſtians firſt invoked God by that title, being thereunto moved by the Holy Ghoſt, who thereby declared to the unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jews,</hi> that they were the Sons of God, and his heirs, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs through Jeſus Chriſt. But then ſaith he, as it were correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, if they did call God Father in their devotions, they did it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of their own proper motion, whereas the Gifted Chriſtian Orators did it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the Spiritual Energy of the Holy Ghoſt, and there was as ſenſible a difference (ſaith he) between calling God Father from thoſe two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as between ſpeaking in acquired tongues, and tongues by Inſpiration, or healing by Phyſick, and the gift of the Holy Ghoſt; whereof the latter carried along with them a viſible divine impreſs, and therefore the Spirit which moved the Chriſtians to cry <note n="*" place="margin">Paracletus ipſe teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dicit dono quod datum eſt nobis: non enim nos <hi>Abba</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus ſine teſte &amp; à nobis ipſis, virum paracleti donum eſt, &amp; ipſe docuit nos per ſpiritum, id eſt, donum ſic loqui in orationibus. <hi>Theophyl. Rom. 8.16. See Gal. 4.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Abba</hi> Father in their devotions might well be called the <hi>Spirit of adoption, which thereby bore witneſs with their Spirits that they were the ſons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence I paſs to the <hi>diſcerning of Spirits,</hi> which was as uſeful a gift as any of the reſt. For as in <hi>Egypt</hi> Satan raiſed up <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> and other Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49584:12"/> to contend with <hi>Moſes</hi> in working of Miracles: So in the Primitive times of Chriſtianity he raiſed up ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conjurers, and Magicians, who as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, Came after the working of Satan with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders,</hi> of whom our Saviour propheſying in the 24th <hi>chap.</hi> of St. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel ſaid, that <hi>they ſhould ſhew great ſigns, and wonders, and deceive if it were poſſible the very</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Compare <hi>Ex.</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. and 14.2. and 26.18. with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9. and 5.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22.</note> 
               <hi>Elect,</hi> that is, <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Compare <hi>Ex.</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. and 14.2. and 26.18. with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9. and 5.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22.</note> 
               <hi>Church it ſelf.</hi> They had power from the Devil (as St. <hi>John</hi> plainly ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.14. and 16.14.) to work ſigns and wonders in the air; to ſpeak diverſe Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; to foretel Plagues and Storms; to tell what was done at a diſtance; to make fire come down from Heaven; to vomit flames; to walk and fly in the air, and caſt out Devils by a compact with <hi>Beelzebub</hi> their Soveraign Prince. And all theſe things they did to confront the Miracles and invalidate the Authority of the Apoſtles, and confirm this Anti-Chriſtian doctrine, which was a contradiction to their Goſpel, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was not Chriſt. For this reaſon they are called in the forecited places Antichriſt, and falſe Prophets, and there were very many of them, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as <hi>Simon</hi> called <hi>Magus, Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer, the ſeven ſons of <hi>Sceva</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> and many more not mentioned in the Scriptures, as <hi>Barchozbah,</hi> and <hi>Apollonius Thyanaeus,</hi> who aped our Saviour, as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Sorcerers imitated <hi>Moſes,</hi> in as many Miracles as he could do, and was the Prince of all the Devils Apoſtles, and the greateſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician, that ever deceived the world.</p>
            <p>God therefore in compaſſion to the ſtate of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church inſpired the <hi>Governments</hi> in all places with a ſupernatural Sagacity to diſcern theſe <hi>Satanical</hi> ſpirits, and diſtinguiſh their works from thoſe of the Spirit of God. One of the principal rules, which the diſcerners of Spirits gave to the Church whereby to try the Spirits, was this: that every Spirit, which wrought Miracles
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49584:12"/> to prove that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the Chriſt, was of God; but every Spirit, that wrought wonders to prove, that he was not Chriſt, or that another was the Chriſt, was a lying Spirit, that Spirit of Antichriſt, which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our foretold his Diſciples ſhould come, and which was in the world in the time of St. <hi>John,</hi> as you may read in the place I cited before, as alſo in his 2 Epiſt. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. Conformably to this St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>verſe</hi> before my text, lays down the ſame infallible rule that no man that calleth <hi>Jeſus</hi> Anathema, as many Infidels and Apoſtates did, can ſpeak by the Spirit of God. Another rule whereby to try the Spirits was ſubmiſſion, and obedience to the Governours of the Church. <hi>We are of God:</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> 1 Ep. 4.6.) <hi>he that knoweth God heareth us; he that is not of God heareth not us: hereby we know the ſpirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error.</hi> And <hi>If any man among you</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37.) <hi>pretend to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet or inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, as a ſign that he is truly ſo, let him acknowledge, that the things I write unto you are the Commandments of God.</hi> I queſtion not, but they had other teſts beſides theſe, by which to try the ſpirits, as that every ſpirit which wrought ſigns to confirm any doctrine, which was inconſiſtent with a pure and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life, or the ſober uſe, and rules of moral reaſon, muſt needs be a diabolical Pſeudo-prophetical ſpirit, as I think I could demonſtrate, if I had but time.</p>
            <p>From whence I come to ſpeak of the two laſt kinds, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. in <hi>1</hi> Ep. ad Cor. <hi>12.</hi> c. Hom. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gift of Tongues,</hi> and which was as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful as that, the gift of <hi>Interpreting</hi> thereof. To the underſtanding of which be pleaſed to take notice that the gift of ſtrange tongues was uſually accompanied with ſuch ſtrong Enthuſiaſms, and Raptures, that the affected perſon could not uſe his underſtanding in an ordinary way, ſo as to <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. ib.</note> interpret, and explain his inſpirations in the audience to which he ſpoke; which was the reaſon that the ſpirit did uſually reveal to <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.4, 28.</note> others, who ſtood
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49584:13"/> by and underſtood not the inſpired Languages, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which the gifted Oracles ſpoke, or elſe by a <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſ. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10</note> new inſpiration revealed unto them the things which they had ſpoken in the unknown tongue, but through the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Enthuſiaſm had forgot. Which latter Gift, becauſe it was more profitable for the Church, the Apoſtle in the 14th <hi>chap.</hi> prefers before the former, which the vain <hi>Corinthians</hi> did ſo much affect.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the miraculous gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which as it appears from the 28. <hi>ver.</hi> of this <hi>chap.</hi> God gave to the difference of Miniſteries, or Miniſters, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers, Helps</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the Primitive Church. To the <hi>Teachers, i. e.</hi> to the more profound and ſolid ſort of Doctors, who anſwered to the <hi>Scribes</hi> in the Synagogue, and wholly devoted themſelves to Preach, and expound the Scriptures, which was an excellent Gift, or Talent, and always eſteemed the moſt uſeful way of inſtruction (eſpecially of the <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.27. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 28.23.</note> 
               <hi>Jews</hi>) in the Primitive Chriſtian Church. To the <hi>Helps, i. e.</hi> to the helpers, or aſſiſtants, ſuch as the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts were to the Apoſtles, as <hi>Silas</hi> to <hi>Paul, Mark</hi> to <hi>Barnabas,</hi> or ſuch as the Deacons were to the Biſhops, and Presbyters, and the whole Church. And they are called helps by an Hebraiſm in Greek, as the <hi>Levites</hi> were called in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church and Language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>helps to the Prieſts.</hi> By <hi>Governments</hi> are to be underſtood Governours, for in the Helleniſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſtyle the abſtract is often put for the concrete, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Syriack</hi> tongues, and by Governours are meant the <hi>Apoſtles and</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">So <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. The Angel of the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. for <hi>trying</hi> them, which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to whom the Gift of diſcerning Spirits ſeems to have belonged in a peculiar manner, becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is here put for Government, is uſed by the <hi>Septuagint</hi> to render the Hebrew word <hi>Tachbuloth,</hi> which ſignifies diſcerning Wiſdom, Prudence, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, wherein the ſpirit of Government doth conſiſt.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49584:13"/> Thus in the <hi>firſt</hi> of <hi>Proverbs v.</hi> 5. where we ſay, <hi>a man of underſtanding ſhall attain unto wiſe counſel,</hi> the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a man of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall attain unto Government.</hi> The like may be ſeen <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.14. and 14.6.</p>
            <p>There were other Miraculous gifts under the New Teſtament, which are not mentioned in this Chapter, and which though properly ſpeaking they did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Holy Ghoſt, yet in a large ſenſe may be called <hi>ſpiritual gifts.</hi> Theſe were the <hi>voice from Heaven,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> called <hi>Bath col,</hi> and the appearance of Angels thoſe holy meſſengers of God, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits, who ſometimes acted as Gods Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.2.</note> aſſumed his perſon in ſpeaking to men. But though the Apoſtle take no notice of them here, becauſe they were not intrinſecal, and inherent gifts, yet I thought fit to mention them becauſe they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and relate to ſome paſſages in the following part of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you an account of the number, and diverſities of theſe gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the difference of <hi>Miniſteries</hi> to which they belong'd, I proceed in the Third place to ſhew the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why they were given by God to the Primitive Churches, and not to the Churches of latter times.</p>
            <p>Now this reaſon is to be taken from the wants and neceſſities of the Primitive Church, whoſe <hi>infant-ſtate</hi> required, that God ſhould aſſiſt her with the Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Gifts of the Spirit, till the Goſpel was ſufficiently Preach'd about the Empire; the Scriptures of the New Teſtament compleated; the Temple-worſhip aboliſhed among the <hi>Jews;</hi> Idolatry deſtroyed among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and both were united together under Chriſt into one Communion, or Catholick Church. It had been impoſſible for God to bring to paſs all theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49584:14"/> ſtupendous things in a way conſiſtent with his own Wiſdom, and the freedom of humane nature, without making uſe of theſe, or other fitting means, as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful as theſe, to publiſh the Goſpel, and confirm the truth thereof. How ſhould the Jewiſh and Gentile world have believed without Apoſtles, and <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.25.</note> Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Preachers, and how ſhould the Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts have preached, unleſs they had been inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? for their Saviour left them like Orphans, or rather like Scholars of the third Claſſe, before he had revealed all the Goſpel unto them, and therefore it was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for God to ſend his Spirit the Comforter to ſupply his place among them, to build upon the Foundation, which he had laid, and diſcover the word of Wiſdom in as ample manner unto them, as they were to Preach it about the world. And then becauſe they were il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate men, that knew no Languages but their own, it was requiſite for him to give them, and their aſſiſtants the gift of <hi>ſtrange tongues,</hi> that they might freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with men of all countries, and Provinces, and Preach the Goſpel through all the world.</p>
            <p>But then as the Spirit qualified them by infuſed Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Languages to preach: So was it requiſite for him to confirm the Truth of their doctrine by Signs, and Wonders, as by giving them Power to ſilence Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and rebuke Magical ſpirits, to caſt out Devils, heal the Sick, raiſe the Dead, and demonſtrate his ſpecial Preſence in Chriſtian aſſemblies by ſending his Spirit upon private men, and Idiots, and in particular by enabling them to ſpeak in ſtrange tongues, which by reaſon of the rapturous way in which they were inſpired, they could not interpret to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, in which they ſpoke. This manner of ſpeaking in unknown tongues is different from that, which I mentioned a little before. For the former way of ſpeaking was given to the Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49584:14"/> not ſo much for a ſign, as to enable them to inſtruct fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein nations in the Faith, and it was either a permanent gift, or if it were not, it always came upon them in a calm and gentle manner, inſomuch that they were perfect maſters of their own underſtandings, and could freely converſe with the people, to whom they ſpoke.</p>
            <p>But the uſe of the latter was principally <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>Signal,</hi> or <hi>Teſtimonial,</hi> like other miracles, and came upon the people, as well as the Miniſters, and that in ſuch a rapturous Enthuſiaſtical manner, that though they underſtood their <note n="‖" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.4.</note> own inſpirations, yet they were not able to interpret them to the Church, and therefore to this gift was uſually annexed the more uſeful gift of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting tongues, of which I ſpoke before.</p>
            <p>All theſe Miracles are called the Teſtimony of the Spirit, particularly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. God the ſender of the Spirit is ſaid to have <hi>born the Apoſtles witneſs, with ſigns, and wonders and divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Hither we may alſo refer the <hi>word of Knowledge,</hi> or the gift of Prophecy properly ſo called, which of all the Unctions of the Holy Ghoſt was a particular ſign to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that the Chriſtians were alſo the children of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, upon whom the Spirit of Prophecy came. But then it was requiſite for them upon other accounts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the diſcovery of things ſecret, and remote, and the prediction of future events was frequently neceſſary for the preſervation of the Chriſtians, and preventing of imminent danger to the Church. Thus <hi>Agabus</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying by the Spirit, that there ſhould be a great dearth throughout all the world, <hi>i. e.</hi> all <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hum.</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.7.</note> 
               <hi>Judaea,</hi> the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples at <hi>Antioch</hi> determined before-hand to ſend relief unto their Brethren in <hi>Judaea</hi> by the hands of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> So an Angel was ſent to <hi>Paul</hi> to aſſure him, that he ſhould be brought before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and that God would ſave all the lives in the ſhip for his ſake. By which Revelation he was enabled both to encourage,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49584:15"/> and direct the Sea-men, who had otherwiſe given up all in deſpair. Hither I may alſo refer the prediction of our Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.15, and 16. <hi>verſes,</hi> which the believing <hi>Jews</hi> remembring, when <hi>Gallus</hi> ſo providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially raiſed the ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> immediately went out of it, and fled to the Mountains, inſomuch that when <hi>Titus</hi> ſome months after beſieged the City, there was not one Chriſtian in the <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. Ecc. Hiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> place.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the Spirit of Preaching, Praying, and Praiſing God by Inſpiration, or Prophecie improperly ſo called, was requiſite for the ſtate of the Primitive Chriſtian Church, for by this the Circumciſion was alſo convinced, that <hi>God was no reſpecter of perſons, when they ſaw</hi> to their aſtoniſhment, <hi>that on the Gentiles alſo were poured out the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> This was the reaſon why the Apoſtles did by Solemn Prayer, and Impoſition of hands confer theſe, and other gifts of the Holy Ghoſt upon <hi>Baptized Gentiles,</hi> to convince the <hi>Jews,</hi> that the Chriſtian Religion was to be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and that Chriſt was the Saviour of no leſs than the whole world. Furthermore they were neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Faith, and warm the devotion of the Newly Converted Chriſtians, who were very apt through the deluſion of Hereticks, and Satanical ſpirits to Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, and renounce Chriſt, as likewiſe to convince the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> unbelievers, whom curioſity brought to the Chriſtian Aſſemblies, that <hi>God was in them, and among them for a truth.</hi> Laſtly, as St. <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 43. <hi>vid. &amp;</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Clement,</hi> who was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s fellow-work-man, aſſures us in his firſt Epiſtle to theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who were ſo rich in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al gifts, theſe and other gifts were ſent upon the people as divine indications to the Apoſtles, whom they ſhould Ordain Biſhops, and Presbyters and Deacons in the Cities and Countries which ſhould be converted to the Faith. So the Apoſtles directed the Diſciples to look out among themſelves Seven men of honeſt report,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49584:15"/> and full of the Holy Ghoſt whom they might ordain Deacons. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt Epiſt. to <hi>Timothy</hi> 4.14. charged him not to neglect the <note n="*" place="margin">Calvin Inſtit. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> gift of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which was given him by Prophecy, and the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his hands. And accordingly <hi>Euſebius</hi> out of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> reports of St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; in locum.</note> that he took men to ordain Biſhops of the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Churches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from among thoſe who were ſignalized with ſpiritual gifts. Agreeable to which <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> told their Predeceſſors, that the Holy Ghoſt had ſet them over the flock.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Becauſe it was impoſſible to govern the Church more than other Societies and Bodies politick without ſenſible puniſhments, God endowed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and their Succeſſors with a power of inflicting ſupernatural diſeaſes; and death upon incorrigible of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, while for want of aſſiſtance from the Secular arm, they had not power to make penal laws for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. This ſupernatural power of inflicting corporal puniſhments, which uſually accompanied excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, made the <hi>Apoſtolical rod</hi> as terrible <hi>as the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that walketh in darkneſs, and the deſtruction that waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at noon day.</hi> For by it offenders were delivered up to Satan to be tormented, poſſeſſed, and killed by him, who is the <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 2.6. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14.</note> ordinary executioner of Gods judgments. And it was ſo inherent at that time in the Apoſtolical function for puniſhing of Scandals, and preſerving the Unity and Order of the Church, that God was pleaſed to ſecond their dreadful Cenſures in their abſence, as well as their preſence, as upon the <hi>incestuous Corinthian,</hi> whom this Apoſtle <hi>delivered up to Satan</hi> in an <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5</note> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical meeting at <hi>Corinth,</hi> although he was not there. And ſuch a tender regard had God for the Order, and Diſcipline of the Church, that he concurred with the Apoſtles in the execution of this power, not only againſt thoſe who continued obſtinately in <note n="‖" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5</note> inceſt, <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17.</note> blaſphemy,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49584:16"/> hereſies, and ſuch like ſins, but againſt thoſe alſo, that were prating malitious Schiſmaticks, oppoſers of the Biſhop, and diſturbers of the peace, and order of the Church. Such an one was <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper-ſmith, and <hi>Diotrephes</hi> in the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whom S. <hi>John</hi> aſſured the Church he <note n="*" place="margin">3 <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> would remember (<hi>i. e.</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) when he came, for his evil deed. We cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that our Lord, who came not to deſtroy mens lives but ſave them, would have given the Apoſtles ſuch a power over mens lives, but in order to ſuch a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable end. It was neceſſary, that they, their aſſiſtants, and Succeſſors the Biſhops (who are likewiſe called Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.25.) ſhould be inveſted with this power to preſerve their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as Governours, and thereby ſecure the diſcipline and government of the Church: which as ſuch is a <hi>Spiritual body politick</hi> conſiſting of Magiſtrates, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and ſo ought to have its proper laws. Therefore God, who in his infinite wiſdom could not erect a Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty without Governours, nor conſtitute Governours with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inveſting them with a ſufficient power of caſting contumacious tranſgreſſours out of their Government, thought fit in the Churches minority to execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon thoſe, whom they ejected; in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, I conceive, conſiſted their miraculous power of inſlicting ſupernatural diſeaſes, and death. A power more than Imperial, and greater than <hi>Caeſar</hi> could ſhew, which made their Eccleſiaſtical ſubjects reverence their perſons, and dread their diſpleaſure, and by conſequence ſhews, that it was put into their hands in that exigence, as the Sword is put into the hand of the Secular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that they might be a terror to evil doers, and aſſert their Spiritual government over the Church. This is plain from the ſtory of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> whoſe ſudden miraculous death was a terror to the reſt (for as the text tells us, great fear came upon all the Church)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49584:16"/> and plainly ſhews that the Church was not a mere volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Society nor the Apoſtolical authority precarious, but the undoubted Ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>From all which I hope it is plain that the neceſſities of the Primitive Church were the reaſon, why God gave theſe gifts of the Holy Ghoſt to Her, and not to the Churches of later times. And this is apparently aſſerted by the Apoſtle in the 4th <hi>chap.</hi> of his Epiſt. to the <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in ep. ad Eph. c. <hi>4.</hi> Hom. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> where after he had ſpoken of the <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophyl.</hi> upon the place.</note> gifts, which our Saviour gave in different meaſures to the ſeveral Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church, to the <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. id.</note> 
               <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. id.</note> 
               <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> ſaith, <hi>that it was for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying the body of Chriſt, till they came in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> From <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. Quaeſt. ex E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang.</note> whence it is evident, that as the Goſpel increaſed, and the Church grew up, God, like a wiſe nurſe, weaned her by degrees from theſe miraculous gifts, till at laſt having arrived at her full ſtature in Chriſt, he left her, as Parents leave their children, when they are grown to be men, to ſubſiſt without extraordinary helps and ſupplies. And therefore as the Scriptures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, God ceaſed by degrees to diſcover the doctrines of the Goſpel by Inſpiration to the Miniſters of the Church, and by that time the writings of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were made up, and the <hi>Scripture-canon</hi> as it were Sealed, the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles in the time of <hi>Clemens, Polycarp,</hi> and <hi>Papias,</hi> (the Diſciples of S. <hi>John</hi>) and of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> pretended to no other way of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or coming to the knowledge of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than by the <note n="‖" place="margin">Apoſtolorum Succeſſores &amp; Diſcipuliſacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum libros, iis qui fidei ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem nondum audiviſſent, tradebant.</note> word of God.</p>
            <p>And then as the Goſpel began to be Preached in <hi>Latin,</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> and native <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Graecians</hi> were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Miniſters of the Word, the Gift of tongues,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49584:17"/> which was the firſt of the gifts of the Spirit, began to grow uſeleſs, and ceaſe. Till at laſt Churches being gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all Provinces of the Empire, and every Nation having Miniſters of its own, the Goſpel was Preached without Inſpiration in all languages of the world.</p>
            <p>The gift of Prophecy properly ſo called continued ſomewhat longer in the Church, becauſe in theſe times of danger, and perſecution, it was neceſſary for Chriſtians (as I ſhewed before) to be forewarned of future events. <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> hiſt. c. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, that <hi>Quadratus</hi> and <note n="‖" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ammius Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphenſis</hi> who lived in the beginning of the Second Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury together with the daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> (the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) had the gift of foretelling things to come, and cites a paſſage out of the dialogue of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> with <hi>Trypho</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> wherein he aſſerts that <hi>Prophecy</hi> was ſtill to be ſeen in the Church. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> alſo <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 57. reckons the Prophetical influx in Viſions, and predictions among the ſpiritual gifts, which he ſaith the Diſciples in that age received in different meaſures for the good of the Church. <hi>Origen</hi> alſo in his Seventh Book againſt <hi>Celſus</hi> mentions this among other miraculous gifts which were then extant. But though at that time the Prophetical ſpirit was ſtill in being, yet it was very extraordinary, and ſoon after ceaſed altogether in the Church.</p>
            <p>We read of the power of raiſing the dead in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited paſſage of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who ſpeaking of his own time ſaith, <hi>And now the dead are raiſed, and have lived among us many years.</hi> But the gift of healing being ſo beneficial to mankind continued longer in the Church, (as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent out of <note n="*" place="margin">Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <note n="‖" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> contra Celſ.</note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> but little or no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of it after, till the latter end of the Fourth, and beginning of the Fifth Century, when God was pleaſed to work that and many other <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Chryſ. Hom. <hi>37.</hi> in S. Jul. Hom. <hi>43. in S.</hi> Mach. de S. Bab. contr. Gentiles. Aug. Ep. <hi>137.</hi> ad ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; pleb. Hippon. Chryſ. Hom. <hi>69.</hi> En. com. Mart.</p>
                  <p>Aegypt. Aug. l. <hi>22.</hi> de civ. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i c. <hi>8.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etract. c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Miracles at the tombs, and by the Reliques of Martyrs, which were the laſt Miracles in the Church.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49584:17"/>
            <p>As for Miracles (ſpecially ſo called) they alſo began to grow ſcarce about the latter end of the Second Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, after God had ſufficiently ſealed the truth of the Goſpel by them, and in ſpite of the powers of hell brought the world to embrace the Chriſtian Faith. But yet becauſe there ſtill remained an <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> gave Oracles in <hi>Daphne</hi> the pleaſant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of <hi>Antioch</hi> in the time of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi> the Ap. <hi>Chryſ. de S. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylá Mart. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Gentiles.</hi>
               </note> Oracle now and then to be ſilenced, a Pythoniſt to be exorciſed, a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical ſpirit to be rebuked, or an inſulting and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Demoniack to be diſpoſſeſſed, God continued them upon theſe; and <note n="‖" place="margin">As upon the building of the <hi>Temple</hi> by the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time. <hi>Naz.</hi> 2. <hi>invect. contra Julian. Marcell. lib.</hi> 22.</note> ſuch like occaſions longer in the Church, and yet they too <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. contra Manich. &amp; de ver. relig. lib. <hi>1.</hi> retract. c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ceaſed about the beginning of the Fifth Century when <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. de S. Babylâ.</note> 
               <hi>Idolatry</hi> was almoſt quite extinguiſhed, and when the Church built Her Faith not on preſent but paſt Miracles, and her <hi>Hieroms, Auguſtins,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> like us were not inſpired, but ſtudied Divines.</p>
            <p>As for the gift of <hi>Praying, and Preaching by the ſpirit,</hi> there is no mention made of it in the Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, even where they enumerate the reſt of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual gifts. Unleſs <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>57<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Euſeb. hiſt. lib. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> comprehend it under the gift of ſtrange tongues, with all ſorts of which, he ſaith, many of the brethren ſpoke in his time by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. Neither need we wonder that there is no further account to be found of it out of the Apoſtles writings, ſince the Chriſtians might learn what to pray for, and how out of the Scriptures, which are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent rule of devotion, as well as Faith, and ſince that gift was alſo rendered uſeleſs by the <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſſand. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turg. Dr. Ham.</hi> View of the new Directory.</note> early general uſe of Liturgies, wherein the Church made Offices for the Sacraments, for the Ordination of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, for the Catechumeni, the Penitents, and Poſſeſſed perſons, and Supplications and Prayers, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49584:18"/> Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks for all men, for Kings and all that were in Authority in a good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable manner through the name of the only Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor betwixt God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Thus exſpired theſe miraculous gifts of the Spirit, the actual communication and exerciſe of which the Apoſtle in the 7. <hi>ver.</hi> of this <hi>chap.</hi> calls <hi>the manifeſtation of the Spirit,</hi> and ſaith, that they were given to every man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the benefit and advantage of the Church. But as the Church grew up from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant to her full ſtature in Chriſt, ſo they grew uſeleſs, till at laſt ſome ſooner, ſome later, they were quite taken away. This St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who could do all Miracles, foretold in the 13th <hi>chap.</hi> of this Epiſt. wherein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to covet the ſaving rather, than the miraculous Graces of the Spirit, becauſe theſe ſhould, but thoſe ſhould never fail. Charity (ſaith he) is a gift that never faileth, but other gifts ſhall, for whether there be <note n="*" place="margin">Si enim Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiae, &amp; lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae ſunt propter ſuſceptionem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei, ſide undi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> explicatâ, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſuperflua ceſſabunt in praeſenti, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè autem in futuro. Theoph.</note> Prophecies they ſhall fail, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be <note n="*" place="margin">Si enim Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiae, &amp; lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae ſunt propter ſuſceptionem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei, ſide undi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> explicatâ, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſuperflua ceſſabunt in praeſenti, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè autem in futuro. Theoph.</note> tongues they ſhall ceaſe, or whether there be knowledge it ſhall vaniſh away. For we know, what we know by Revelation, but in part, and we Propheſie by inſpiration but in part, but when the perfect knowledge of the Chriſtian Religion, or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate of the Church is come, then that which is imperfect and obſcure ſhall be done away. Even as when I was a child I <note n="‖" place="margin">Dicit <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tanquam ad <hi>linguas</hi> referat. id.</note> ſpake as a child, I <note n="*" place="margin">Hoc ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetias referre videtur. id.</note> underſtood as a child, I thought and conceived things as a child, but when I became a man, and to the full uſe of my reaſon, I put away childiſh conceptions and things. For now we ſee Divine Revelations as the Prophets did of old, in a dark Enigmatical manner, and by Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal repreſentations of things upon the fancy as in a glaſs, but then in the adult ſtate of the Church, we ſhall ſee them after the <hi>Moſaical</hi> manner in a more rational way
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49584:18"/> and more accommodate to humane nature, as it were face to face. Now I know them imperfectly, but then I ſhall know them clearly, even as I am known. To conclude, there are three permanent gifts, Faith, Hope, and Charity; but the moſt excellent of theſe is Charity.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſcourſed Firſt of the kinds of Spiritual gifts, and Secondly of the number, and variety of that miraculous ſort, which is underſtood in my text, and having in the Third place ſhewed the reaſons, which moved God to give them to the Primitive Church, and not to the Churches of latter times, I proceed in the laſt place to make ſome improvement of the whole diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I deſire you to reflect on the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Saving, and Miraculous gifts of the Spirit, and then to conſider how much more excellent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable the former are, than the latter, and how much rather you ought to covet theſe than thoſe, although they were extant yet in the Church. As for theſe they neither ſuppoſed any ſaving Grace in the gifted perſon, nor brought any along with them, nor drew any after them, but as <note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Hom.</hi> 29.</note> S. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> compares them to riches, ſo like riches they tempted men to <note n="‖" place="margin">Chryſ. in Eph. <hi>4.</hi> Hom. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Pride, Vanity, and contempt of their Governours, as alſo to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theoph.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.1.</note> envy, and hate one another, ſo that this Apoſtle was fain to make uſe of the ſame Apologue, to allay the envy of ſome and the grief of other <hi>Corinthians</hi> (who had none, or not ſo many, or not ſuch ſpiritual gifts, or not to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree as others had) as <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> did to appeaſe the Commons of <hi>Rome,</hi> by comparing the body politick of the Church to the natural body; which cannot be all head, hand, or eye, but hath ſeveral members ſome more honourable than the other, and all conſpire to the good of the whole. Nay ſo inconſiderable are theſe gifts in themſelves, and ſo unprofitable to any Chriſtian,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49584:19"/> as to his main concern, that <note n="*" place="margin">Reſſ onſ ad quaſt. <hi>5.</hi> ad Orthodox. in Juſtin Mart. Auguſt. de Serm. domini.</note> like the ſun and rain they were given to good and bad, and when they were given to a truly good Chriſtian they could not ſecure him in a ſtate of Grace, for they could not reſtrain theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> from many grievous ſins, with which the Apoſtle chargeth them, nor, as it appears from <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. <hi>verſes,</hi> keep others from a final Apoſtaſie from Chriſt. This, I ſuppoſe, was the reaſon, why our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when his Diſciples returned with joy, ſaying, <hi>Lord, even the devils are ſubject unto us in thy name,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them thus: <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 130.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoyce not in this that the devils are ſubject unto you, but rather rejoyce that your names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of life.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks this Apoſtle to the vain <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who valued themſelves ſo much upon the account of their ſpiritual gifts. <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. tract. <hi>13.</hi> in Evang. Joh. qui habet ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam ſponſus eſt. <hi>Cyprian. de unit. Eccleſ.</hi> Nam &amp; prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare &amp; damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia excludere, &amp; virtutes magnas in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris facere, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limis utique, atque admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis res eſt, non tamen regnum coeleſte conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur quiſquis in his omnibus invenitur, ſi non, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Though, ſaith he, I could not only ſpeak with all the tongues of men, but expreſs my thoughts like Angels, and have not Charity, I ſhould be no better than a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical inſtrument of braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal. And though I had the gift of Propheſying, and underſtood all Myſteries, and had all knowledge revealed unto me, and though I had the higheſt degree of miraculous Faith, ſo that, as our Lord ſaid, I could remove mountains, and yet had no Charity with them, I ſhould be good for nothing, nor become in the leaſt more acceptable to God. The tongues of men or Angels, to ſpeak in the Apoſtles phraſe, could have ſaid nothing more plain or emphatical to ſhew how much more excellent the ſaving graces of the Spirit are, than the miraculous gifts, which can neither render us like God, nor quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us for the enjoyment of him, and which gave no intrinſecal worth to the perſons, who formerly had them, nor made them more uſeful for the Church, than acquired gifts, which are the ordinary means of Faith, and Repentance, make us. Suppoſe thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the Goſpel, like the Apoſtles, by Inſpiration, what
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49584:19"/> then? another Miniſter, who knows it by reading and ſtudy is as capable to ſerve the Church as thee: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if thou art, like a vain <hi>Corinthian,</hi> ambitious of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, know that it will add nothing to the reputation of thy parts, for an inſpired man is but the veſſel to the treaſure, the very inſtrument and Machine of the Holy Ghoſt, who can ordain ſtrength out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings, and make a child, or an idiot, preach as well as thee.</p>
            <p>Or ſuppoſe thou hadſt the ſpirit of Prophecy, what then? The knowledge of things paſt being as excellent in it ſelf, and generally more uſeful to the world, than the knowledge of things to come, the hiſtorian would have as much to boaſt of as thee. Nay hiſtorical know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hath the advantage above the Prophetical, not only in this, that it is more clear and diſtinct, but that it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a great deal farther, for the greater face of <hi>Janus</hi> hath long been ſet behind, to ſignifie unto us, that the world is grown old, and that many more ages are gone than are to come. But it is an honour to be a Prophet of God? and it is a greater honour to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, the ſervant of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt; but if thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the burden and pangs of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Habak.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23.9.</note> Prophetical viſions, and the terror of Prophetical dreams, thou wouldſt, like ſome of the greateſt Prophets of old, deſire God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that honour on ſome other man.</p>
            <p>But thou wouldeſt have the gift of healing, why ſo? Is it that thou wouldſt take pleaſure in doing good? for the ſame reaſon thou mayeſt wiſh, that all thy Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponds were pools of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> or that thou hadſt all the riches of the world: but if thou haſt but Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and loveſt thy neighbour, <hi>i. e.</hi> mankind, as well as thy ſelf, thou art as excellent a Chriſtian, and as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, as if thou wert an inſpired <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> and hadſt Cured all the Hoſpitals in the world. Or what if thou hadſt this wonderful beneficial gift? Thou haſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49584:20"/> contributed nothing to the having of it, for the bones of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and of the <note n="*" place="margin">Gervaſius, &amp; Protaſius. Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de civ. dei c. <hi>8.</hi> retract. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Milan Martyrs</hi> had that, as well as thee.</p>
            <p>But perhaps thou haſt a mind to the gift of tongues? What if thou hadſt it? an acquired linguiſt would do the Church as much ſervice as thee, and would really have more reaſon to boaſt of his learning, for God can make an Oracle of, an <hi>Aſs,</hi> and Timber and Stones ſpeak <hi>Latin, Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Greek.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if thou couldſt do Miracles: what if thou couldſt? <hi>Hereticks</hi> have done them, and <hi>Judas</hi> did them, and yet was the worſt of men, and many ſhall ſay unto me in that day, <hi>Lord! Lord! have we not propheſied in thy name, and in thy name done many wonderful works? and then I will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thou art a Miniſter, and wouldſt fain preach by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, why ſo? not out of <hi>Corinthian</hi> vanity, and oſtentation; for then thou art a vain-glorious man; but becauſe thou haſt a deſire to convert more ſouls; but alas, thou art not ſure of that, for the words of this inſpired Apoſtle were a ſtumbling-block unto the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and a ſcandal to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> even the ſavour of death unto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who heard him. And the Souls of thouſands, who heard inſpired Sermons from Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and ſaw them alſo work Miracles, lye roaring now in the flames of hell.</p>
            <p>But to pray by the Spirit is a moſt deſirable gift; ſo it would be indeed if thou like the Novice-converts of old knoweſt not <hi>how,</hi> nor <hi>what</hi> to pray for as thou oughteſt. But thou canſt cry <hi>Abba, Father,</hi> without inſpiration, and thou mayeſt make prayers, and ſupplications, and interceſſions, and giving of thanks for all men without inſpiration, which, if thou hadſt it, would not make thy prayers more excellent in themſelves, or more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of God. For whoſoever hath a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49584:20"/> devout Soul, and approaches God with that reverence, which is due to his infinite Majeſty, and heartily asks, what he would obtain in the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, his conceived, nay his <hi>book</hi> devotion ſhall prevail as much at the Throne of Grace, as if it were inſpired. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired prayers are a Teſtimony of God's love? ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking I believe they were, but ſo are croſſes, and afflictions (which immediately proceed not from our own ſin and folly) and yet thou art not deſirous of them, although they are ſigns of Adoption, or publick teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials by which God hath declared to his Church, (which he never did of inſpired perſons) that <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are not Baſtards, but Sons. From all which it appears how much more excellent, and deſirable the ſaving Graces of the Spirit are, than all theſe pompous miraculous gifts, in which there is really no intrinſecal excellence, nothing why we ſhould deſire, or expect them further, than as they may be uſeful for the Church, inſtruments of Religion, and motives to Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in defect of ordinary means, and acquired gifts. All which I would have thoſe eſpecially to conſider, whoſe Enthuſiaſtical tempers, or educations encline them firſt to admire, and then to conceit theſe miraculous gifts, till by inſenſible degrees they impoſe upon their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and commence within themſelves illuminated men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I proceed to ſhew what little reaſons the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors have to make <hi>miracles a ſign of the true Church.</hi> For Miracles were formerly wrought for ſigns to confirm the Authority of the Apoſtles, and their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Succeſſors, and to ſeal the truth of that new doctrine, which they were to preach about the world. Therefore to ſuppoſe that the Church ſtands always in need of Miracles is to ſuppoſe her to be ſtill in a ſtate of Minority, and her doctrine to be always a publiſhing to the world, or elſe to ſuppoſe, that infinite wiſdom may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49584:21"/> become impertinent, and ſeal the ſame truths, ten thouſand times over. Indeed, as they argue, in the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> there were always miracles to be found, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their <hi>Theocratical</hi> conſtitution of Church and State was miraculous, God as their King being obliged to make known his pleaſure in Civil and Military, as well as in Eccleſiaſtical matters unto them by <hi>Voices from heaven, Oracles,</hi> and <hi>Prophecies</hi> (as other Princes do by Proclamations, and meſſages) and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were always to work ſigns and wonders to prove the Truth of their miſſion, and ſometimes the certainty of what they foretold ſhould come to paſs. But then beſides the miracles, which belonged to the nature of their <hi>Theocratical</hi> Government, God wrought others for them, and among them, to render himſelf, and that particular Church more conſpicuous in the eyes of the <hi>Gentile</hi> world. Hither we may refer their miraculous victories by ſingle men, or armies over their enemies, which God wrought, to convince them by ſenſible expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments of his Omnipotence, that of all the <hi>divinity</hi> of the Eaſtern world he alone was the true God. But had the <hi>Law</hi> been publiſhed among all Nations, like the Goſpel, and <hi>Judaiſm</hi> become the Univerſal Religion of the world, Miracles at length would have grown out of uſe, as indeed they grew very rare after the <hi>Jews</hi> were diſperſed among the Nations, and their Law was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into <hi>Greek,</hi> which at the time of the Tranſlation was become the moſt general Language of the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I proceed to ſhew you how unreaſonably the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath acted in verifying the Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal pretenſions of ſo many groſs Impoſtors and Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts as ſhe hath done to Inſpiration; Propheſie; Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Dreams; Familiar converſes with God, and the glorified perſon of our Saviour; working of wonders; Communion with Saints, and Angels; Raptures, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, and all other ſorts of Miraculous gifts, that we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49584:21"/> read of in the Primitive Church. Such as theſe were <hi>Dominic, Francis</hi> of <hi>Aſſize, Francis</hi> of <hi>Pole, Francis Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius, Ignatius</hi> the founder of the Jeſuits, <hi>Genvieve, Tireſia, Catherin</hi> of <hi>Siena, Brigit,</hi> and many more of both Sexes, whom ſhe hath not only Canonized for Saints, but to the great ſcandal of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath incorporated Religious Societies of men and women to live according to their pretended inſpired rules. For which not only the Common people, and the Brethren, and Siſters of the Orders, but their Learned Doctors pretend to have as great, (and, it may be, a greater) veneration, than for the Goſpel it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I proceed to ſhew you what a ſandy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation the Popes Infallibility is grounded upon. For it muſt be reſolved into this Enthuſiaſtical principle of immediate Inſpiration, which according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I have now Preached, neither he, nor any other <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Presbyter</hi> of the Church, hath warrant from the Scriptures to pray for, or expect. I ſay it is a moſt dangerous, and Fanatical pretenſion, which is ſo far from having any ground in Scripture, that it makes it a moſt imperfect and uſeleſs rule of Faith, deſtroys the certainty of the Chriſtian belief, which was fixed above Sixteen hundred years ago, and inſtead of being a means of ending controverſies, as Papiſts pretend, it introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces everlaſting Scepticiſm into all the parts of Divinity, by making truth, or falſhood, good, and evil, light, and darkneſs, ſweet, and bitter, nay what ſhall I ſay? by making right and wrong, God and <hi>Belial,</hi> Chriſt and Anti-chriſt depend upon the breath of a ſingle man.</p>
            <p>In the Fifth place, let me ſhew you what a dangerous, damnable, and precarious principle that is, which <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>George Reiths</hi> immediate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1676.</note> aſſerts, that immediate Revelation, or Inſpiration is not ceaſed, but is a ſtanding, and perpetual gift in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49584:22"/> the Church of Chriſt, belonging to the very ſubſtance of the Goſpel-Covenant, and of indiſpenſable neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the whole body, and every member thereof. And that this ſpirit of immediate Revelation or Spiritual light, is not, like the <hi>Spirits</hi> in Primitive times, to be tryed by the <note n="*" place="margin">Barclay<hi>'s</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>or</hi> Apologia Theolog.</note> Scriptures, and reaſon, but that both of them are to be tryed by it. This doctrine differs from the preceding only in this, that, that makes only the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but this makes every private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian a Pope, and as it utterly overthrows the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Scriptures, and makes them an uſeleſs rule of Faith: So hath it already caſhiered the uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and annulled the Miniſterial Orders, contrary to the Precepts and Precedents of the Goſpel, and the practice of Gods Univerſal Church. And when time ſhall ſerve, it can as effectually convert the Profeſſors of it into down-right Popery conſiſtently with their own principles, for they have nothing more to do, than to ſay that the Spirit hath told them that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the only true Church, and that <hi>ſupra hanc Petram</hi> belongs to the Pope. As this doctrine was firſt privately ſowed among us by <note n="‖" place="margin">Foxes and Fire-brands, <hi>pag.</hi> 15. &amp;c. Printed, 1680.</note> Popiſh Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo hath it been publiſhed in our and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries by thoſe, who were Papiſts, as by <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> who was bred in the Scottiſh Covent at <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Labbade</hi> a Jeſuit defrooqued.</p>
            <p>In the next place to montion will be ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the <hi>Pſeudo-Prophetical</hi> Spirits of this age, ſuch as <hi>Nayler, Venner,</hi> and <hi>Muggleton,</hi> with his companion <hi>Reeve,</hi> who call themſelves the Lords Two laſt Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and Prophets, and have framed many tracts, and letters from <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Holy Spirit, a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which may be had in Print. I deny not, but that God is free to ſend Prophets when he pleaſes, and that he may do ſo, when the exigence of the Church doth require it; but then whenſoever he ſends them,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49584:22"/> he will, as he hath always done, ſend them with the power of working Signs and wonders, and whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſhall come, we ſhall have a right to try them by the Scriptures, as a <hi>Teſt.</hi> But for theſe, and the <hi>German</hi> Prophets, who pretended to Inſpiration, and Prophecie without ſigns; to voices from Heaven, which none heard; and ſtrange Apparitions, which none ſaw but themſelves; and who Preached other doctrines, than what the Apoſtle hath preached, they were En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſts, or Impoſtors, or a compoſition of both, and had they firſt appeared in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> had likely careſſed them for great <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> offered them the compliment of a new <hi>Order,</hi> and ſo have obliged them, as he hath done many more by the ſame arts, to devote themſelves to his ſervice, and declare him to be <hi>Vice Deus, Vice Chriſtus,</hi> a God upon earth, the Soveraign both of Angels and men.</p>
            <p>In the next place let me obſerve unto you, that among all the <hi>miraculous gifts of the Spirit</hi> recited either in this <hi>Chapter,</hi> or any other place of the Goſpel, there is no mention made of <hi>Heroical impulſe,</hi> by which men were ſometimes irreſiſtably moved from the Spirit, under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy to execute judgment in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial manner upon the enemies of God. For God being the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ</hi> 33.22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.11. <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.28.37.40. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11.</note> 
               <hi>Political</hi> King, and Legiſlator of the <hi>Jews,</hi> did as other abſolute Monarchs do, in ſome ſpecial exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies ſend men with extraordinary ſupra-legal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to do preſent execution upon great and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous offenders without ſtaying for the ordinary proceſs by Law. But our Saviour, one end of whoſe coming was to put an <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26, 27. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35.</note> end to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy, and who <hi>came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them,</hi> gave no ſuch gifts unto men. No, there is to be no <hi>fire from Heaven,</hi> nor no <hi>Phinehaſes</hi> under the Chriſtian diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Accordingly the firſt Apoſtolical ages of wonder were utterly ignorant of <hi>killing impulſe</hi> and <hi>zeal,</hi> which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49584:23"/> I could not but obſerve to the utter deteſtation of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Aſſaſſins,</hi> the <hi>Clements,</hi> and <hi>Ravilliacs</hi> on one hand, and the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Knoxes</hi> hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Ravilliac re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divivus,</hi> and the hiſtory of the late Arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the <hi>ſpirit of Popery.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melvils,</hi> and <hi>Mitchels</hi> on the other.</p>
            <p>To proceed, Let us a little more particularly reflect upon that blaſphemous doctrine of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (now by the induſtry of the Emiſſaries no contemptible Sect) concerning a <hi>Spiritual miniſtery,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual worſhip,</hi> whereby they pretend that the Holy Ghoſt now comes down upon their Aſſemblies, as it did in the Apoſtles time, and moves them to preach and pray by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without any regard to condition, or Sex. Hence when they meet together they ſit hanging their heads in a ſilent dumb manner, till the Spirit, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, ſhall move ſome body, it is indifferent be it man or woman, to preach or pray. Accordingly they call their Preaching, <hi>Propheſying,</hi> and precariouſly ſay that they have the <hi>Spirit of Adoption, by which they call God Father,</hi> and that the ſpirit in the inſpired Miniſter <hi>maketh Interceſſion for them with unutterable groans.</hi> That they groan ſufficiently, we grant, for ſometimes in their meetings they do nothing elſe; but if their groaning, or vocal devotions be from the Spirit, how comes it to paſs, that the Spirit never moves them, as it did in the Apoſtles days, to Pray and Propheſie in unknown tongues? When we ſhall ſee in their Aſſemblies, as the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> did in the Primitive Chriſtian meetings, that they have the gift of tongues, and the gift of interpreting thereof; when together with the gift of tongues, we ſhall ſee that they have, as the Chriſtians had, all the other miraculous gifts; when we ſhall ſee that they ſhew themſelves to be <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Spiritual</hi> in receiving what this Apoſtle hath written (in particular, <hi>that a woman ſhould not ſpeak in the Church) as the Commandments of God,</hi> and laſtly, when with all this they ſhall preach no other doctrine, than what the Apoſtle hath preached, and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49584:23"/> Church received, then we will believe, if they be lawfully baptized, that <hi>it is the ſpirit which is ſpeaking in them, and that God is in them and among them of a truth,</hi> but till then we muſt believe them all to be Impoſtors, or Enthuſiaſts, and blaſphemers of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the next place let us conſider, what an horrible ſin it is to counterfeit any of the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, in particular the <hi>ſpirit of Praying and Preaching,</hi> which, with the <hi>gift of Faith</hi> as it is taken for <hi>inſpired courage and boldneſs,</hi> is moſt eaſie to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited of all the ſpiritual gifts. But firſt let us make ſome reflection on the pretenders to the <hi>ſpirit of praying and preaching,</hi> under whom I comprehend not only thoſe whom I mentioned above, but another ſort of <hi>ſpiritual juglers,</hi> who when they are aſhamed to talk, like the loweſt form of Enthuſiaſts, in a plain Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſtrain, and ſo apparently blaſpheme the Holy Ghoſt, yet invent ſuch uncouth ambiguous terms in Divinity, and ſo artificially contrive the ſtyle and phraſe of their religious diſcourſes, as to beget an opinion in their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, that they pray and preach by inſpiration, and ſo beſides the diſhonour they reflect on the Chriſtian Religion, and the Holy Ghoſt, maintain the Schiſms which they have made, under the colour of more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ordinances and worſhip, and ſacrilegiouſly uſurp that ſpecifick veneration to themſelves, which was wont to be given to inſpired men. One equivocal phraſe which is commonly in the mouths and writings of theſe Sanctimonious men is the <hi>Spirit of preaching,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit of prayer,</hi> which, though by an <hi>Hebraiſm</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they ought now to ſignifie no more than the skill, or habit of praying, and preaching, yet theſe Sophiſters and uſurpers (for ſo moſt of them are) of our Holy Profeſſion ſo uſe them, that the deluded people generally take them in a more obvious ſenſe for praying and preaching by immediate inſpiration from the Holy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49584:24"/> Ghoſt. To this purpoſe they talk much of the <hi>in-come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, out-lettings,</hi> and <hi>in-dwellings</hi> of the Spirit, and have taught their diſciples to object, that to <hi>pray by a form doth ſtint the ſpirit,</hi> and by theſe, and other like phraſes, whereof ſtore may be found in <hi>Rutherfords letters,</hi> and the writings of the <hi>Independents,</hi> not to mention any more, they have made their followers take it for granted, that extemporary prayers, eſpecially as they are ſpoken, and acted by them, are the effect of inſpiration, and by conſequence, that themſelves are immediately inſpired. This error concerning the extemporary ſpirit of Prayer hath been the cauſe of much <note n="*" place="margin">Concil. Milev. <hi>2.</hi> can. <hi>12.</hi> Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, ut preces, quae probatae fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rint in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio ab omnibus celebrentur, nec aliae omnino di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ, ne fortè aliquid contra fidem vel. per ignorantiam vel per minus ſtudium ſit compoſitum. <hi>See alſo</hi> Con. Carth. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> miſchief to the Church, and of much diſhonour to the name of God. It hath cauſed men to have a mean opinion of Forms, although our Saviour not only taught his Diſciples to pray by a form, but prayed by a form when he hang'd upon the croſs. It hath made them reject all <hi>Liturgies,</hi> and <hi>Liturgical offices,</hi> contrary to the practice of Gods Univerſal Church; nay it hath made theſe Spiritual Mountebanks not only diſ-uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> it ſelf, but forbid the uſe of it as Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, Idolatrous and <note n="‖" place="margin">See D. <hi>Owens</hi> life.</note> a Papiſtical charm. By this the people of theſe kingdoms have been led into the moſt <hi>unnatural</hi> Schiſm and Rebellion that ever was, not to mention the later <hi>Murders, Rebellions,</hi> and <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> which the Separatiſts from our <hi>Siſter Church</hi> have committed, raiſed and carried on by the help of this deluſion; and they may Preach, and Pray the people to what they pleaſe, as long as they hold them captive under this error, which is not only inconſiſtent with what I have now delivered concerning the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, but contrary to the practice of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and it may be confuted, would people but reflect, by the example of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> among the <hi>Jews;</hi> and the flagitious lives of many Chriſtians, as of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſaub.</hi> of Enthuſiaſm.</note> 
               <hi>Baſilides</hi> the bloudy Tyrant of <hi>Maſcovy,</hi> the late <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49584:24"/> of theſe Three Kingdoms, the <hi>Founder of the Jeſuits, Labbadé,</hi> Major <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Ravil. rediv.</note> 
               <hi>Weer,</hi> and Captain <hi>Venner,</hi> who of all Enthuſiaſts, or Impoſtors that ever pretended to Pray by the Spirit, were in this ſenſe the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and eloquent, for they had <hi>words</hi> and <hi>tears,</hi> and <hi>ſighs</hi> at command, and ſo bewitched the people by their rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous ſpiritual-like devotions, as to paſs for men extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily inſpired.</p>
            <p>Which brings me to reflect on the arrogance and preſumption of ſome ſort of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who warranting themſelves from the promiſes, which God made of his ſpecial preſence to the Prophets and Apoſtles, and the ſpirit of <hi>ſupernatural courage and confidence,</hi> which reſted upon them by virtue thereof, have treated Kings and Princes with a counterfeit ſort of Prophetical bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if God, as he ſpoke to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, had hardned their foreheads like flint or Adamant,</hi> or had made them, as he told <hi>Jeremiah</hi> he would make him, like an <hi>Iron-pillar, and brazen wall againſt the whole land, both againſt King and Prieſts, and Princes and people.</hi> Hence with incomparable rudeneſs, and inſolence, they have contrary to all rules of Chriſtian Charity libelled and upbraided inſtead of humbly reproving their King, and all under the pretence of <hi>preaching the word with boldneſs,</hi> and as if God had ſent them on purpoſe, as he ſent <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> to <hi>David, Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or <hi>Elijah</hi> to <hi>Ahab, &amp;c.</hi> they have called Proteſtant Princes <hi>Perſecutors, Idolaters,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboams</hi> to their faces, and told them that God would deſtroy them and their houſe. Nay they have preſumed in Gods name to lay <hi>civil injunctions,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions</hi> upon them and their Courts of Juſtice, and when the Magiſtrate hath commanded the people to do one thing, they have charged them to do another. With the like counterfeit ſpirit of Apoſtolical boldneſs, but of real unchriſtian impudence and railing, they have ſpoken evil of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical <hi>dignities</hi> to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49584:25"/> great diſhonour of God, and his Prophets, and Apoſtles; who never ſpoke nor acted any thing by virtue of any ſpecial miſſion, and the ſpirit of courage which did attend them in it, but what was conſiſtent with gentleneſs, moderation, humanity, duty, and love.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place give me leave to ſhew you, how much ſome Authors have injured the Chriſtian Religion, and abuſed the unlearned part of the world, who writing the lives of ſome modern <hi>Enthuſiaſtical Divines</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented them as endowed with moſt of theſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spiritual gifts. Thoſe, who deſire to be ſatisfied in this particular, may conſult the life of Dr. <hi>Samuel Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In the 9. <hi>p.</hi> of the <hi>praeſ.</hi> the Author ſaith that he ſaw the sky open, and heard a voice which ſaid to him, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor his ſhould ever want: which cannot be true, for his ſon went a begging, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 41. of the book. In the 10. <hi>pag.</hi> God aſſured him that he ſhould have a ſafe voyage into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and convert many ſouls there, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 41. Once when he prayed for a ſick perſon in another land, he had an aſſurance of the parties recovery, by an <hi>audible voice, and a glorious brightneſs</hi> which ſhined round about him, <hi>ib.</hi> When he was a School-boy, God (he thought) aſſured him by a <hi>vocal anſwer</hi> that he heard his prayer, <hi>p.</hi> 2. When he was very ſick he aſſured his wife, that he ſhould not dy, becauſe <hi>God had not fulfilled a certain promiſe</hi> which he made to him. <hi>p.</hi> 4. He <hi>converſed with Angels in a dream,</hi> and <hi>had ſhewed unto him the exceeding weight of glory, which is laid up in heaven for Gods choſen ones, p.</hi> 17. He lay a whole day in an <hi>heavenly rapture,</hi> and deſired his wife, a Miniſter, and other friends to tell him, <hi>whether he were in the body, or out of the body, for he could not tell, p.</hi> 24. Before he prayed with Coll. <hi>Jones</hi> his wife when ſhe was ſick, he asked her <hi>whether ſhe had faith to be healed?</hi> and when he had done praying he aſſured her ſhe ſhould live, <hi>p.</hi> 44. His hearers could tell by his prayers for ſick perſons, whether they ſhould recover or not, <hi>p.</hi> 47, 48. he knew the ſame himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 50. When his wife lay under a temptation to turn <hi>Anabaptiſt, God aſſured him by prayer,</hi> that he ſhould be quickly ſatisfied from heaven, <hi>p.</hi> 51. Mrs. <hi>Winters</hi> Siſters husband lying very ſick at <hi>London,</hi> ſhe ſent to the Dr. at <hi>Dublin</hi> to pray for him, but before he could be perſwaded to pray, he retired privately to <hi>know of God if he were yet alive,</hi> and after prayer aſſured the company, that he ſhould recover. <hi>p.</hi> 52, 53. Once praying in imitation of <hi>Abrahams</hi> interceſſion for <hi>Sodom,</hi> as he kneeled againſt a poſt in the room, he ſaw a <hi>great ſhining light about him, and perfectly heard a voice ſaying, The Nations ſhall be ſpared for ten thouſand righteous ſake, p.</hi> 56. He uſed to pray for things, and have his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before he roſe from his knees, and immediately give thanks thereupon, <hi>p.</hi> 56. He often heard voices, when none heard them but himſelf, according to <hi>Acts</hi> 22.9 <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note> Provoſt in the late times of <hi>Trin. Coll.</hi> by <hi>Dublin,</hi> and what is written of old Mr. <note n="‖" place="margin">Whom that Author <hi>calls the man of God,</hi> and ſaith that Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> called him the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Prophetical and Apoſtolical man of God.</hi> He ſtruck a man dead upon the place, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> with a word, <hi>p.</hi> 252. He told one <hi>John Steward</hi> of <hi>Aire,</hi> who came to viſit him in priſon, that the Plague of God was broken out in that place, and bid him haſten home, and cauſe <hi>Heugh Kennedy</hi> Provoſt of that town, to convene the people in the ſtreets, and pray together, and the Lord ſhould hear <hi>Heugh Kennedy</hi> and remove that ſtroke. Which (ſaith he) fell out in every thing as the man of God had foretold, <hi>ib.</hi> At the ſiege of St. <hi>Jane de Angeli</hi> he deſired the Canonier to diſcharge ſuch a piece of Cannon, aſſuring him, that God ſhould direct the ſhot, <hi>p.</hi> 254. He aſtoniſhed the King of <hi>France</hi> with a few words, and made him ſay, <hi>Surely, this is a man of God, p.</hi> 255.</note> 
               <hi>Welſh,</hi> and other <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Miniſters, In <hi>the fulfilling of the Scripture,</hi> printed 1669. From whence, not to mention other examples, it will appear, that unleſs God in mercy rebuke that Spirit of Enthuſiaſm, which is gone out amongſt us in theſe Three Kingdoms, we may have as many <hi>Legends</hi> from ſome ſort of Proteſtants, as we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49584:25"/>
            <p>There are excellent uſes, which might be made of what I have ſaid upon this ſubject. 1. Concerning the greatneſs of the Apoſtolical, or Epiſcopal power, as we find it exerciſed by this Apoſtle over thoſe, who were inſpired. For by virtue of that Eccleſiaſtical Authority, which he and the other Apoſtles received from Chriſt, and derived upon their Succeſſors the Biſhops, he ſilenced the <hi>Propheteſſes,</hi> regulated the ſpeaking of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> commanded that not above two or three <hi>inſpired linguiſts</hi> ſhould ſpeak at one meeting, and that not all together, but every one in his turn. But if there happened to be no Interpreter, then that they ſhould all keep ſilence in the Congregation, and only ſpeak mentally to themſelves. In a word he commanded that all things ſhould be done decently, regularly, and according to his appointment. He reproved them for coveting the gift of tongues, and told them plainly, that if any man thought himſelf a Prophet, or any other ways inſpired, he ſhould ſhew himſelf to be ſuch in receiving his orders, as the commandments of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Concerning the uſefulneſs of humane learning, and the neceſſity of erecting Schools, and Univerſities for the teaching thereof. For the Chriſtian Religion cannot be ſupported againſt its adverſaries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out humane learning <hi>inſpired</hi> or <hi>acquired.</hi> And therefore as the Apoſtles, and Apoſtolical preachers died, God
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49584:26"/> ſupplyed their mortality, by calling Philoſophers, and other Learned men to the rational defence of the Goſpel againſt <hi>Jews,</hi> Heathens and Hereticks, whom the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer had redargued not ſo much by <hi>words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> as by <hi>the demonſtration of the ſpirit, and of power.</hi> Nay among the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves there were <note n="*" place="margin">Theſe ſchools of Prophetical Education were at <hi>Naioth</hi> in <hi>Ramah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.19, 20. at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.14. at <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.3, 4, 5. and at <hi>Gilgal,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.38.</note> Schools of the Prophets, in which as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> writers agree, the youth were trained up by ſtudy and diſcipline for the reception of the Prophetical Spirit, which according to <hi>Maimonides,</hi> whom the <hi>Jews</hi> call the ſecond <hi>Moſes,</hi> rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came but upon perſons ſo qualified and prepared. And I dare boldly ſay were it not for the <hi>two Schools of the Prophets in our Iſrael,</hi> that the Nation would ſoon be overrun with ignorance, and Religion quite born down with <hi>Popery,</hi> and other monſtrous Sects among us, which have increaſed with the ſame proportion, that humane learning hath been decryed, and the <hi>Two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities diſ-uſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Concerning the goodneſs and wiſdom of God: his <hi>goodneſs</hi> in ſending his Spirit with miraculous gifts to ſupply the neceſſities of his infant Church, and his <hi>wiſdom</hi> in taking away theſe extraordinary means, when ordinary means were to be had. But I have been too tedious already. God grant that what I have now delivered ſo plainly on this ſubject, may conduce to make us all have right and worthy apprehenſions of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which however it hath ſuffered by ſome mens Enthuſiaſtical Notions, and zeal, yet ingenuous and teachable ſouls (and ſuch there are among the moſt erroneous Sects) will eaſily diſcern from the frame and tenour of this diſcourſe, that, as it was deſigned by its bleſſed founder, ſo it really is the moſt rational, ſober, and regular inſtitution that he could have given to the ſons of men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
